So let's go ahead and jump back into the code.
As we can see here, we have a lot going on right now,
and since we're talking about a new concept in regards to fetching async data,
let's go ahead and clean this up a bit, right?
So I'm going to migrate this over into a separate scratch pad.
So inside of components,
I'm going to just create a scratchpad.view file,
and we're just going to migrate everything from app.view over.
That way, you have that as reference for later on if you want to see exactly what happened.
So we'll clean this up and keep this a standard new,
basically a news app. Great.
I'll go ahead and commit that to the branch.
See, get refactor, move code to scratchpad.
All right. So the question here is the data we've been working with so
far, like if we take a look at scratchpad,
everything is something that we've defined ourselves,
and we're assuming basically that we always have full control of the data.
If that were really the case for front-end development,
I think our lives would be a lot easier.
But the reality is we have to fetch data from the back-end a lot of times,
and we got to figure out how to deal with that.
So if we take the tools that we have right now and think about how we might do that,
let's go ahead and use the Poke API,
which is one of my favorites when it comes to working with sample data,
because I think Pokemon was a fun thing for me growing up as a kid,
and so basically this is a pretty impressive database in terms of being able
to fetch things about individual Pokemon, fetch it by region.
It's darn impressive.
So the URL we're going to be using,
I'm going to go ahead and add a comment up here,
is this pokeapi.com,
and you'll notice the main thing is that it just fetches the Pokemon,
and it limits it to the first 151.
So in other words, the original 151 Pokemon.
So our first goal here is to say,
okay, how do we fetch that data down from the back-end and actually render it onto our page?
Well, first thing first, let's go and set up our app real quick.
We'll export default and object,
and for our reactive data property,
let's go ahead and just have a Pokedex array.
Then again, let me actually add some items in here so we can actually see it when we show it on the page.
Let's go ahead and show that real quick to make sure everything is wired up correctly,
and there you go, our array is showing up.
The next thing we want to do is add some method,
because we need to actually call this thing.
So you might think, okay, so we have a method called fetch Pokemon,
and it will use the fetch API,
and then we'll go ahead and grab this URL up here.
Whoops, there we go.
Then what we need to do though is that often time when you fetch data from the back-end,
you need to actually JSONify it.
In other words, you need to convert it to JSON so you can actually parse it correctly on the front-end.
So the way you do that is you take the response that you're given and you do response.json.
So what we want to do though is we don't only want to fetch this,
we want to actually assign this to our Pokedex.
So we're going to do this top Pokedex equals fetch.
But we're not quite done because what?
Fetch is an async operation,
and right now everything we're writing is in a synchronous operation.
So in other words here, what we got to do is we got to say,
hey, we have to wait for fetch to finish before we do this thing,
and since we need to await the thing,
we need to actually make sure we tell view,
hey, by the way, this is an async function.
This is going to happen asynchronously.
Great, we have our method and so all right,
we want to fetch the thing, right?
So let's say, okay, so we have a button,
and when we click the button,
this is when we want to run that fetch Pokemon.
So fetch Pokemon like that.
Great, let's see what happens now.
If we click, hey, everything's there just as we expect.
This is exciting.
But if we think about the real-world scenario,
while there are cases where you'll be running
async functions on specific user interactions,
the reality is a lot of times when someone's loading a page,
that's probably when you're actually going to be wanting to fetch that data,
and more importantly, you want to fetch it
at a specific time frame.
And so this is where the concept of lifecycle hooks
comes into play when we're talking about front-end frameworks,
and I think most of them do have them.
So let's take a look at the diagram for lifecycle hooks for view,
and we're going to take a look at the one directly on the docs
because I want you all to be able to kind of get familiar with the docs
because view has an entire team dedicated
to trying to make sure that the docs are as top-notch as they can,
and that basically this information is free and available to you
whenever it's time for you to dive into these problems.
And so if we take a look at here,
here we can see an actual diagram of how the lifecycle works,
and so you can see that view, what it starts to do is the renderer kicks it off,
and then it runs a setup lifecycle hook,
which again, we'll talk more about later.
But you can see that what it's doing is it's going through
and at each of these steps where you see the rounded, outlined rectangle,
so we have setup, before create, created, before mount,
all of these are different points inside of the lifecycle of a component,
and what that means is you can actually basically interject different code
depending on where you need it to run.
So for example, you see here that what is it doing?
First, it starts to encounter the component,
it starts to initialize the options API,
and then it starts to do some checks basically, right?
And then it starts to render the component,
it'll actually mount the thing to the actual window.
Basically, you're starting to actually see the thing,
and then finally, if you're deleting something,
it will unmount the thing from the DOM.
And so to be clear, I do not expect any of you
to understand the full effect of what's happening here,
but suffice to know that you can refer to this at any point in the future
when you're starting to get a little bit more nuanced about where you want your code to run.
For the purposes of our exercise, though, we have to think about it like this.
If we wait for the component to mount before we actually start running the code to fetch,
we know that asynchronous calls can take a while,
and what we want to do is try to improve our user experience
by ensuring that users get that data as quickly as possible,
which means what?
We want to actually try to initiate that fetch before the component even renders to the screen.
That way, you call it, we try to time it,
so that by the time the component hits the screen,
you're hoping that the async data basically has hopefully finished by then.
And so if we take a look at where that is,
basically the way to think of it in your head at this point
is mounted is the point when the mount to lifecycle hook
is when it's basically showing up on the screen.
That's the way to think about it.
And so in other words, you have the ability to say before mount,
there's one right here,
but then there's also a couple of steps happening before before mount,
so actually we even have the created lifecycle hook and the before create.
But there's a key thing that you'll notice here though,
is that with before create, this is happening before the options API.
And so what does that mean?
I think it'll be easier if I show you this inside of the code.
So let me go ahead and bump this over.
Okay, so if we take a look at this right now,
we mentioned yesterday that passing an object in order to define
how our component is working is called the options API.
As you see here, there are data, there are methods.
And so similarly, we have the ability to call lifecycle hooks on it.
So we have what we see earlier before create was one of them.
And so before create can be a function that we run.
And so all I'm going to do here is I'm going to log before create.
And then we're going to try to log this.pokedex.
And then we're going to log the created lifecycle hook.
So basically, this is basically how you're going to call
the individual lifecycle hooks, is by basically the name right here
that we see here.
This is a little small right now because of the mobile responsive.
And then just basically calling it as a function.
That's how you actually reference it.
And so when created now, now we'll do a log create.
And then this sign, this is when it's been created.
And this time, we'll log this.pokedex.
Okay, what's going to happen here?
Well, if we take a look inside of our dev tools,
you'll notice something here is that before create gets logged,
but then this.pokedex does not exist.
However, then once created does, you'll
see that pokedex does exist.
And inside of this proxy here, you'll
see that inside of the target, which you want to open up,
that's where you see the actual value of what's happening.
And so if we think about it in another way,
if we rearrange this for our mental model,
before create is actually happening,
all this stuff below here even exists.
And so if that's the case, that means
that when you're using the options API,
before create is probably not actually the best place
to be running an asynchronous function,
because at this point, nothing exists.
So what we want to make sure we do then
is to basically say when it's been created.
Remember, created is not the same as mounted.
There's a bunch of stuff happening before it's actually
mounted to the page.
Once it's been created, this is where we're going to say,
let's kick off our function.
So what we can do is we can then go this.fetch Pokemon.
Now we save this, though.
You'll see, boom, all of a sudden,
without clicking anything, it did exactly what we wanted to,
which is the user hit the page.
The view did its thing to go fetch the data.
It immediately showed up on the screen.
OK.
How do people feel about those concepts?
Does that make sense?
Question.
Are those hooks promised aware if you
were to return the promise to this fetch Pokemon?
Would it pause continuation until it returned?
So your question here is around whether the lifecycle hooks
are aware.
Oh, can you actually just return a promise instead?
Would the created not continue until the promise resolves,
if you wanted to, for some reason, not mount,
but until the promise is fully resolved?
Before you actually move on to the next hook, basically?
Yeah.
So in this regard, you don't want to run it.
I don't see why that wouldn't be possible.
View usually has ways for you to break those things apart
so that you can basically stop it.
And so this would be, to be clear,
this is a little bit beyond the scope of the intro,
so if this goes a little beyond your current knowledge,
don't worry.
But basically, if you've heard of things like next tick
inside of code bases, that's where
people are manually initiating different stages
to ensure that either different frames are being skipped
or moved on.
And so just know that if you're trying to intentionally
stop it at the likes of the code, you'd probably
have to dig into it just to figure out how that will work.
Because normally, as you can see, it tries to optimize it.
Because normally, you might even expect, at this point,
let me go back to the code.
Let me close that.
This.FetchPokemon is an asynchronous function.
And so here's the thing.
If we were to call the fetch directly here,
and we did an await, OK, so let me do this real quick.
And then let's just consResponse equals this.
And let's just logResponse, OK.
So, all right.
You'll see already that view is yelling at me.
Because if you actually manually define it in a way keyword
inside of a lifecycle hook, it will ask
that you actually define the async on that directly.
However, since we're not doing that,
since we actually have the async already defined on the function,
this is why this code still works.
But otherwise, to your question, yeah,
I would just dive further in into how to get it to pause.
But otherwise, you should be able to do what you want.
So when it comes to lifecycle hooks, basically, I would say
the ones to really know about are created.
Because that's usually where you're
going to be running your async functions.
And then if you really have something
that you really want to happen right when the component is
mounted, then I've seen a lot of before mount or mounted
used for those scenarios, where you might want to time
either some sort of animation or that kind of thing.
But otherwise, just know that created
is going to be your bread and butter when using the options
API for doing asynchronous calls.